Inventory of the Papers of Gordon M. Buck
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Inventory of the Papers of Gordon M. Buck
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 88 - 2
16 boxes (7 linear feet)
Gordon Mountjoy Buck was born in 1875 and practiced law in New York city during the 1920s and 30s. This collection consists of professional legal papers and a small collection of personal material. The Buck papers might be useful for research of railroad and corporate litigation, or simply for insight into the workings of a Wall Street law firm in the 1920s and 1930s.
The papers were given to the University of Virginia Law Library by Buck's daughter, Mrs. Charles LeGrand, in 1988.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Gordon Mountjoy Buck was born in 1875. He earned a bachelor of laws degree from the University of Virginia in 1898, and was admitted to the bar in 1900. He is listed in Martindale's American Law Directory as working at 120 Broadway, New York City, in 1912, and at 165 Broadway two years later.
By 1921, Buck was working for the firm of Humes, Buck, Smith & Tweed. That firm became Humes, Buck & Smith the following year, and by 1930, Humes, Buck, Smith & Stowell, with offices at 50 Broadway in New York City. The firm had a general practice, with specializations in corporation, probate and financial law. Major clients included Southern Pacific Company and Pacific Oil Company, as well as many other railroad companies.
Buck retired from the practice of law sometime in 1936 or 1937, and returned with his wife to Virginia to live at his Greenwood estate, Whilton. His former firm survives today in New York City under the name of Humes, Andrews, Botzow & Wagner.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Gordon M. Buck (7 linear feet in 16 boxes) consist of professional legal papers and a small collection of personal material. The papers range mainly from the early 1920s to the 1940s and contain records and briefs, memoranda, personal and business correspondence, court transcripts, and railroad trusteeship instruments. There are also several bound volumes of legal forms and documents, as well as case briefs and memoranda. Very thorough—if not entirely complete—records are included for the cases of Bogert v. Southern Pacific Co., Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., the Pacific Oil Co. dissolution, and Young v. Southern Pacific Co.
The collection should be useful to anyone researching drug law, particularly the debate over the decriminalization of marijuana and the rise in drug usage in the 1970s—an era of great ferment for the drug issue in the United States. Clippings, correspondence, legislative testimony, the materials of special interest groups like NORML, and the notes for Bonnie's books convey the thoughts and attitudes that shaped the drug issue during these years. There is a similar, if not as extensive, collection of materials on the insanity defense from the early 1980s.
Organization
The Buck collection is separated into professional and personal papers. The professional papers are alphabetically sorted by case name and generally go from raw drafts of briefs, memoranda and correspondence to the printed materials. There is an extensive collection of general case correspondence in chronological order, as Buck kept it, and the folders list the names of the prominent cases within. The small collection of personal papers includes documents relating to cases against the I.R.S. and the Mexican government, a few pieces of correspondence, and material on the purchase and furnishing of Whilton, Buck's retirement home in the countryside west of Charlottesville.
Contents List
- Professional Papers (Box 1 - 14)
  The professional papers are alphabetically sorted by case name and generally go from raw drafts of briefs, memoranda and correspondence to the printed materials. There is an extensive collection of general case correspondence in chronological order, as Buck kept it, and the folders list the names of the prominent cases within.
  - Bogert v. Southern Pacific Co., 1920-24, (two folders) (Box 1)
    memoranda of law
  - Bogert v. Southern Pacific Co., 1919, 1923-24 (Box 1)
    plaintiff's briefs and memoranda, U.S. District Court
  - Bogert v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d., (two folders) (Box 1)
    defendant's briefs and memoranda, U.S. District Court
  - Bogert v. Southern Pacific Co., 1923 (Box 1)
    plaintiff's and defendant's briefs, U.S. Circuit Court
  - Bogert v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d. (Box 2)
    records and briefs, U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals
  - Chicago, Milwaukee, St. Paul & Pacific Railroad Co., 1925 (Box 2)
    plan of reorganization
  - Continental Trust Co. v. Seaboard Air Line Railway Co., 1931 (Box 2)
    records and briefs
  - El Paso & Southwestern Co., n.d. (Box 2)
    brief for appeal
  - Garland Manufacturing Co. liquidation, 1943 (Box 2)
    U.S. District Court documents
  - Guaranty Trust Co. v. Seaboard Air Line Railway Co., 1937-41 (Box 2)
    correspondence
  - Guaranty Trust Co. v. Seaboard Air Line Railway Co., ca. 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
    records and drafts for briefs
  - Guaranty Trust Co. v. Seaboard Air Line Railway Co., 1931 (Box 3)
  - Haddad v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d. (Box 3)
  - Interstate Commerce Commission ex parte no. 81, n.d. (Box 3)
    agreement
  - New York Trust Co. v. Seaboard Air Line Railway Co., 1931 (Box 3)
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., n.d. (Box 3)
    notes on briefs
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., 1932-40, (three folders) (Box 3)
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., n.d. (Box 3)
    diary notes
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., n.d. (Box 3)
    law clerk memoranda
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., 1931-33, (four folders) (Box 4)
    hearing testimony
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., 1931, 1934 (Box 4)
    miscellaneous documents
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., ca. 1930s, (one of two folders) (Box 4)
    briefs
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., ca. 1930s, (two of two folders) (Box 5)
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., ca. 1930s (Box 5)
    complaint and answer
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., 1933 (Box 5)
    plaintiff's memoranda
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., 1932-35 (Box 5)
    miscellaneous memoranda
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., 1931, 1933 (Box 5)
    testimony and deposition of Francis Schwab
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., ca. 1931-34 (Box 5)
    master's reports
  - Newark Plaster Co. v. Cross & Brown Co., 1935 (Box 5)
    opinion
  - Pacific Fruit Express Co. equipment trust, 1920 (Box 5)
    memoranda
  - Pacific Fruit Express Co. equipment trust, 1920, 1926 (Box 5)
  - Pacific Mail Steamship Co. dissolution, 1940-42 (Box 6)
  - Pacific Mail Steamship Co. dissolution, 1940 (Box 6)
    auditors' report and account
  - Pacific Oil Co., 1920-21 (Box 6)
    office file (correspondence, minutes, by-laws)
  - Pacific Oil Co., ca. 1920-21 (Box 6)
  - Pacific Oil Co., 1920-21 (Box 6)
  - Pacific Oil Co., 1921-26, (two folders) (Box 6)
    board meeting minutes and financial statements
  - Pacific Oil Co., 1928 (Box 6)
    brief of protest re income taxes
  - Pacific Oil Co., 1921-26 (Box 7)
    office manuals, numbers 1-5
  - Pacific Oil Co., 1924-25 (Box 7)
    annual reports
  - Pacific Oil Co. dissolution, 1929-30 (Box 7)
    notes and drafts
  - Pacific Oil Co. dissolution, 1927-30, (three folders) (Box 7)
  - Pacific Oil Co. dissolution, n.d. (Box 7)
  - Pacific Oil Co. dissolution, 1930 (Box 7)
    petitions for receivership, answer and order
  - Pacific Oil Co. dissolution, 1928-30 (Box 7)
    records
  - Pacific Oil Co. dissolution, 1927-29 (Box 7)
    Pacific Oil Co. final report
  - Rockaway Pacific Corp. v. New York, 1922-23 (Box 7)
  - Seaboard Air Line Railway Co., n.d. (Box 7)
  - Southern Pacific Co., 1921, 1930-32 (Box 7)
    miscellaneous correspondence
  - Southern Pacific Co., 1920- (Box 7)
  - Southern Pacific Co. v. Lowe, 1917-18 (Box 8)
  - Southern Pacific Co., 1929-30 (Box 8)
    office manual
  - Southern Pacific Co. equipment trust, 1913-15, 1923 (Box 8)
  - Southern Pacific Co. equipment trust, 1920 (Box 8)
  - Starring v. Kemp, n.d. (Box 8)
    brief
  - United States v. "Confidence", 1912 (Box 8)
  - Venner v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d. (Box 8)
    memorandum draft and notes
  - Venner v. Southern Pacific Co., 1921 (Box 8)
    memorandum
  - Venner v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d. (Box 8)
    defendant's briefs
  - Venner v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d. (Box 8)
    plaintiff's briefs
  - Venner v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d. (Box 8)
    district court briefs
  - Ward v. City Trust Co. of New York, 1904 (Box 8)
  - Young v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d., (two folders) (Box 8)
  - Young v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d. (Box 8)
  - Young v. Southern Pacific Co., n.d. (Box 8)
  - Diary of cases, 1920-30, (two folders) (Box 9)
    Gordon M. Buck
  - Miscellaneous cases, n.d. (Box 9)
    notes and drafts for briefs
  - Miscellaneous cases, 1924-26, 1928, (eight folders) (Box 10 - 11)
    general correspondence
  - Estates, 1930-32 (Box 12)
    correspondence and depositions
  - Forms, ca. 1920s (Box 12)
    bonds, debentures and stock certificates
  - German bonds held by English trustee, 1923 (Box 12)
  - German bonds held by English trustee, 1923 (Box 12)
    memorandum for Southern Pacific Co.
  - Mortgages, 1897-98, 1901 (Box 12)
    documents and lists (railroad companies)
  - Notebook, n.d. (Box 12)
    legal work
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1911, 1914, 1920-21, 1928-29, (two folders) (Box 12)
    agreements
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1913 (Box 12)
    deed
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1911 (Box 12)
    mortgage bonds
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1907-11, (one of four folders) (Box 12)
    mortgages and indentures
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1917, 1930, (two of four folders) (Box 13)
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1881-1924, (three of four folders) (Box 13)
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1924, 1929, (four of four folders) (Box 14)
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1912 (Box 14)
    registers of railroad directors and officers
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1917, 1930 (Box 14)
    release or resignation of trustee duties
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1911, 1930 (Box 14)
    reports
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1908-24 (Box 14)
    satisfaction of mortgage
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1930 (Box 14)
    Southern Pacific Co. correspondence and records
  - Railroad trusteeships, 1907-11 (Box 14)
    transfer of bonds
  - Securities, 1914, 1925-29 (Box 14)
    Southern Pacific Co. (correspondence, memos, I.C.C. orders)
  - Stock Transfer Guide, 1912 (Box 14)
    (state statutes)
  - Stockholding papers, 1930 (Box 14)
    miscellaneous corporations
  - Trusts for Bernard and John Harrison, 1922 (Box 14)
    indentures
  - Wills for Elise Kruttschnitt and Josephine Vignaux, 1926 (Box 14)
- Personal Papers (Box 15 - 16)
  - The Commercial & Financial Chronicle, 1929, (two issues) (Box 15)
  - Bond claim of Samuel H. Buck against Mexico, 1943-56 (Box 15)
  - Bond claim of Samuel H. Buck against Mexico, ca. 1930s-1950s (Box 15)
    State and Treasury Department documents
  - Bond claim of Samuel H. Buck against Mexico, ca. 1930s-1950s (Box 15)
    notes of Gordon M. Buck
  - Bond claim of Samuel H. Buck against Mexico, 1935-56 (Box 15)
  - Bond claim of Samuel H. Buck against Mexico, 1943-55 (Box 15)
    payment vouchers
  - Bond claim of Samuel H. Buck against Mexico, 1935-36 (Box 15)
    affidavits
  - Buck v. Commissioner of I.R.S., ca. 1930s (Box 15)
  - Buck v. Commissioner of I.R.S., 1935 (Box 15)
    newspaper clipping
  - Buck v. Commissioner of I.R.S., 1929 (Box 15)
    Anaconda Mining and U.S. Steel documents
  - Buck v. Commissioner of I.R.S., 1931-39 (Box 15)
  - Buck v. Commissioner of I.R.S., n.d. (Box 15)
    miscellaneous notes and drafts of briefs
  - Buck v. Commissioner of I.R.S., 1935-37 (Box 15)
    records and briefs (docket no. 78422)
  - Buck v. Commissioner of I.R.S., 1936-39 (Box 15)
    records and briefs (docket no. 86040)
  - Buck v. Commissioner of I.R.S., 1936-37 (Box 15)
    exhibits
  - Cards and pamphlets, n.d. (Box 16)
    miscellaneous
  - Pelham Manor (N.Y.) property, 1920, 1922 (Box 16)
    deed, indenture and agreements
  - Personal correspondence, 1930 (Box 16)
  - Personal correspondence, 1930 (Box 16)
    Virginia and the University of Virginia
  - Whilton (Va.) estate, 1936-41, (two folders) (Box 16)
  - Whilton (Va.) estate, ca. 1930s (Box 16)
    miscellaneous paper
- Personal Correspondence, 88 - 2a (Box 17 - 18)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1920-1921, (four folders) (Box 17)
    Miscellaneous
  - Personal Correspondence, 1926-1930, (four folders) (Box 18)